<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The devout soules search with the happie issue of comfort found : in a sermon, preached at Paules Crosse, Ian. 14. 1610 / by Thomas Myriell ...</title>
            <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22108127</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22108127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The devout soules search with the happie issue of comfort found : in a sermon, preached at Paules Crosse, Ian. 14. 1610 / by Thomas Myriell ...</title>
                  <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 91 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.C. for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at his shoppe, at the great South dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸ G⁷.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Mark XVI, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEVOVT SOVLES SEARCH. With the happie iſſue of Comfort found. IN A SERMON, <hi>Preached at Paules Croſſe. Ian.</hi> 14. 1610.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Myriell,</hi> Preacher of the word of God, at <hi>Barnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Bonus es domine, animae quaerenti te. Si quaerenti, quanto magis inuenienti? Si tam dulcis eſt memoria, qualis erit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia? <bibl>Bern.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> For Iohn Budge, and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe, at the great South dore of Poules. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND <hi>FATHER IN</hi> God, the Lord Byſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> my very good Lord, heauenlie grace, and earthlie peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT Reuerend Father in God, &amp; my very good Lord.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere is no ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, to giue life, nor meanes to preſerue life in the affection of loue, as
<pb facs="tcp:25090:3"/>loue it ſelfe. Neither is anie thing ſo kindely to mans nature, or ſo naturall to mankinde, as to loue, when one is beloued.</p>
            <p>Therefore euen hee, which is loue it ſelfe, takes this courſe, hee loues vs firſt, that wee may loue him firſt, and laſt; <hi>Quid tam populare quam gratia?</hi> ſaieth that generous By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Fauour and grace, as we affect and deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more; So, nothing ſo much affecteth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth vs. Hence, my Lord it is, that as by du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:25090:3"/>I muſt not, but honor; ſo by affection, I cannot, but loue your Lordſhip: my ſelfe in particular, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g receiued as good cauſe to doe this, as you giue to others in generall, iuſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doe that.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhips pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mee, doth make me vowe, neuer to forget you. Your kinde affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in wiſhing you might do me good, did me much good preſently, as ſoone as you wiſhed it. And <hi>certes,</hi> I no wayes doubt, (ſuch is
<pb facs="tcp:25090:4"/>your Lordſhips loue and reſpect, with God himſelf in heauen, and his vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, &amp; vice-rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in earth: ſuch your dignitie, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie in the Church and Court,) that anie rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable matter is, or can be ſo difficult, that your Lordſhip may wiſh for it, and yet not haue it.</p>
            <p>I know your Lordſhip looke for no requitall, and indeed I can make none. Yet, if I ſhould not ſo much, as once ſhew ſome willingnes, I ſhould more then make ſhewe of great
<pb facs="tcp:25090:4"/>vnworthineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aeſchines,</hi> a poore ſcholler to <hi>Socrates,</hi> when hee ſaw manie of his companions beſtow great gifts on their maiſter, himſelfe grieuing, hee could not be a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them in giuing rewards, as hee was in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Learning: thus ſaid, <hi>Nihil dignum te, quod dare tibi posſim, inuenio: Et hoc vno modo pauperem me, eſſe ſentio. Itaque dono tibi, quod vnum habeo meipſum. Hoc munus, rogo, qualecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt, boni conſulas, cogite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios, cum multum tibi darent,
<pb facs="tcp:25090:5"/>plus ſibi reliquiſſe.</hi> I can finde nothing to giue you, which is anie way wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of you; and heerein onely, I finde my ſelfe to be poore. Therefore, loe, euen all that I haue, I giue you, that is, My ſelfe. This gift, I deſire you, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſimple, to take in good worth, and to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon of others, that though they gaue much to you, yet they kept more for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. To whom <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> made this anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quidni tu mihi magnum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dederis, niſi forte paruo te
<pb facs="tcp:25090:5"/>aeſtimas? Habebo itaque curae, vt te meliore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi reddam, quàm accepi.</hi> Without doubt, thou haſt giuen me a great gift, vnleſſe thou accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy ſelfe little worth: I will therefore endeuour, that I may reſtore thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto thy ſelfe, better worth then I tooke thee at the firſt. The like gift, my Lord, I a poore <hi>Aeſchines, doe moſt willingly</hi> bequeath to your Lordſhip; &amp; that becauſe I verelie hope, that, with graue and wiſe <hi>Socrates,</hi> you will, ere long, reſtore mee to my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb facs="tcp:25090:6"/>(now ſcarcely <hi>apud me,</hi> through an Ocean of worldlie croſſes) much better then you now find me.</p>
            <p>And for a pledge of this gift, I beſeech your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to accept this rude ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and to giue it your countenance to grace it, and protection, to defend it. And then I doubt not, but, as it was once care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully attended from my mouth, by honorable and religious hearers, ſince, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly requeſted from my hands, by worſhipful and
<pb facs="tcp:25090:6"/>deare friends: So, now, much more, it will be thankfully receiued in the hearts of all deuout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, not, becauſe it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer mine, but for that it is become whollie your Lordſhips. And ſo, humblie crauing pardon of your Lo: for my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I ceaſe further to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you: euer reſting, your Lordſhips humbly to be commanded,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Myriell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25090:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>DEare Christian Reader, (for deare I reade thee, if thou be a Chriſtian,) To thee, I truſt, I need not Apologize for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Sermon. If it profit ſpoken, it cannot but profit written. For other, if any complaine,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>There is no end of making many bookes;</hi> I anſwere, it is meant, of many books made to no end. But for a Sermon, there is great reaſon, as to make it out of a book in the pulpit, ſo to make it into a booke in the Preſſe. Euery good thing, the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, the more commodious. And it is no leſſe griefe to the ſpirituall father, to ſee that his ofspring, (bred of his braine, and brought forth by his breath) ſhould die as ſoone as it begins to liue; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is for the naturall mother, to behold one and
<pb facs="tcp:25090:8"/>the ſelfe ſame day, to be vnto her child <hi>dies natalis,</hi> and <hi>dies fatalis,</hi> a day of birth, and a day of death. And ſurely, wee liue in an age, where all knowledge abounds, ſaue the true experimentall and practicall knowledge of Chriſt, and therefore, wee had need now, with the Prophets of old; to<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.10.</note> 
               <hi>adde praecept vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on praecept,</hi> by ſpeaking, and <hi>line vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to line,</hi> in writting. Theſe reaſons, with the importunitie of many friends, haue made me yeeld to the publiſhing heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Vſe it, and enioy it in the Lord: in whom, and to whome, I leaue thee, euer resting,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. ad licent. epiſt. 41.</note>
                  <hi>Seruus tuus, per ipſum, &amp; conſeruus ſub ipſo. Thomas Myriell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25090:8"/>
            <head>THE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOVT SOVLES <hi>SEARCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark. 16.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But he ſaid vnto them, Be not afraid: Ye ſeeke Ieſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> which was crucified: he is riſen, he is not heere, behold the place where they put him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the wiſeſt of the Sonnes of men had not ſaide it, yet the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the ſonnes of men, had long ſince prooued it, that<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 8.6.</note> 
               <hi>Loue is as ſtrong as death.</hi> Cant. 8.6. <hi>As ſtrong</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25090:9"/>(ſaith <hi>Augustine, in a double respect.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Siue quia nemo eam vincit, ſicut mortem: ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue quia in hac vita vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad mottem, eſt meoſura charitatis. Auguſt. ad Hieron. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 29.</note> Either becauſe no man ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes loue, no more then death; or elſe, becauſe the meaſure of loue extendeth euen vnto death: ſo as the partie louing, ſhrinketh not at the ſharpeſt ſting of death, to expreſſe his affection to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie beloued. Nay, if we ſay, loue is ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger then death, we ſay no more then reaſon will defend, which tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs; Death may extinguiſh life, but is not able to extenuate loue. <hi>Faith and hope,</hi> two great victors:<note n="c" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>but the geeateſt of theſe is loue.</hi> 1. Cor. 13.13. The greateſt, though not for the<note n="d" place="margin">No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſed propter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manentiam. Auguſt.</note> emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie here in this life, yet for the permanency, when this life is done.</p>
            <p>Which threefold ſtrengh of loue, is well exemplified in theſe three, holie women, who loued Chriſt in his life, and<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.3.</note> 
               <hi>miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him of their ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi> Lu. 8.3. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him at his death, &amp;<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 19.25.</note> 
               <hi>wept for him at his Croſſe.</hi> Ioh. 19.25. Loued
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25090:9"/>him after death,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16 1.</note> 
               <hi>and ran with oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and odours, to embalme him in his graue.</hi> Mar. 16.1. Where, their forward deuotion beeing preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his early reſurrection; and their ſorrowful eies (in ſtead of his dead bodie) preſented with the ſight of a glorious Angell: ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their hearts were filled with as much new <hi>fear,</hi> as before they were cloyed with old vexing griefe. But hee which defraudes not good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the due incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, neither denies ſimple deuotion of her right inſtruction, purpoſely ſent his Angell, both to direct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their errour, &amp; to comfort them againſt their feare, which made the Angell according to his charge, kindely to beſpeake them, ſaying: <hi>Be not afraid, yee ſeeke Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words, Right honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Right worſhipfull, and welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Chriſtians, we may conſider
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25090:10"/>two things. Firſt, the perſons ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or doing. Secondly, the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſpoken or done. The perſons, in theſe words, <hi>But hee ſaide vnto them:</hi> And they are two<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell directing, the women enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. The matter in theſe wordes. <hi>Be not afraid, ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>which was, &amp;c.</hi> And it is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. Firſt, the Angells conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Be not afraid.</hi> Secondly, the womens enquiſition. <hi>Ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was crucified.</hi> Thirdly, Chriſts reſurrection. <hi>He is riſen, he is not here: behold the place where they put him.</hi> Of theſe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. And firſt of the perſons.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt of the two perſons: Our Euangeliſts heere calleth him<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16 5.</note> 
               <hi>a young man,</hi> Mark. 16.5. But Saint Matthew plainely, chap. 28.2. calleth him,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.2.</note> 
               <hi>the Angell of the Lord.</hi> An Angell then it was in the forme of a you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man: which outward forme Angels ſometimes vſed, (as one vſeth a garment) to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25090:10"/>put on and off at pleaſure: as alſo their eating of meate, done ſaith Saint Auguſtine,<note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. ad Deogratias, Epiſt. 49.</note> 
               <hi>non neceſſitate, ſed poteſtate:</hi> not by any neceſſitie which was in themſelues, but by a power which they had from God: vſing things agreeable with vs, and carrying themſelues ſuteable vnto vs, that their ſtrangeneſſe might not be terrible, but their familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie comfortable. This Angel there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, being ſent to comfort, not to aſtoniſh, tooke on him the forme of a young man, in his apparition to theſe moſt deuout women. Of a man, a forme cuſtomable, that he might not affright: of a young man, a forme amiable, that hee might delight.</p>
            <p>Now the word <hi>Angell,</hi> ſignifieth a meſſenger. <hi>A name,</hi> ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 104. Ex eo quod eſt ſpi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. eſt: ex eo quod agit, ang lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>officij, non naturae,</hi> declaring an Office, not deſcribing a nature. For in that he is, <hi>he is a ſpirit:</hi> in that he is ſent, <hi>he is an Angell:</hi> but a name wel beſeeming thoſe pure, louing,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25090:11"/>and ready ſpirits, who alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding Gods face in heauen, are readie to execute his commaund on earth. The chiefe of all Gods creatures, excellent in all things, but for three things moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: that is to ſay, purenes of ſubſtance, readines of obedience, feruentnes of charitie. Which three things the Pſalmiſt couertlie notes, Pſal. 104.4.<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.4.</note> 
               <hi>He maketh his Angels ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and his Miniſters a flame of fire.</hi> Hee maketh them ſpirits, there is their pure ſubſtance. He maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Miniſters, there is their readie obedience; he maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a flame of fire: there is their heate of loue. But <hi>Moyſes</hi> declares theſe thinges more plainely, in the making of the Cherubims, which were placed ouer the mercy-ſeate, in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Theſe he made,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 25.19.</note> 
               <hi>of the pureſt golde, with their wings ſtretched out, and their faces one towardes another.</hi> Exod. 25.19. Of the pureſt gold, there is the dignitie of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25090:11"/>for of all mettalls, gold is moſt excellent. <hi>With their wings ſtretched out:</hi> there is the readines of their obedience; for of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, winged are ſwifteſt. <hi>With their faces one towards another,</hi> there is the feruentneſſe of their charitie: for of all the geſtures of the body, none is ſo amiable, as kindly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him in ſight, to whom we are beholden of dutie.</p>
            <p>That their nature is pure, their manſion declares.<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 10.</note> 
               <hi>For they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes behold the face of God, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> Matth. 18.10. Into whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, no impure thing can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.27.</note> Reuel. 21.27. Hence, for their ſhining, they are called <hi>Starres,</hi> and for their brightnes in ſhining,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 38.7</note> 
               <hi>Starres of the morning.</hi> Iob. 38.7.</p>
            <p>That their obedience is ſwift, their name declares. <hi>A quo domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio, ab eo denominatio.</hi> From the the qualitie ſuper-eminent, is the name deriued. Hauing then the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25090:12"/>name of a meſſenger, they are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to be moſt diligent in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting a meſſage. Hence, as for brightnes, they are compared to the ſtarres: ſo for ſwiftnes, they are likened to the windes:<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.10.</note> 
               <hi>Hee rode vpon Cherub, and did flie; hee came flying vpon the wings of the wind.</hi> Pſalm. 18.10.</p>
            <p>That their charitie is moſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, the ſcripture is euident. For euery way they deſire our welfare. Touching our inward eſtate, ſo much wiſh they our greateſt good, that they ioy in our<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>conuerſion to God.</hi> Luk. 15.10. Not only for that by the conuerſion of good men,<note n="i" place="margin">Iacob de vorag. dom. 3. poſt Tri.</note> their number is made vp againe.<note n="u" place="margin">Stell in Luc. 15.10.</note> Nor yet onely for that they ſee ſuch a glorious fruit of their cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and charge; that men by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tace forſake the Tents of vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; like good Chriſtian Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, warre vnder the banner of Chriſt. But alſo, for that, by the conuerſion of the faithful,<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Matth. bom. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Facta
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:25090:12"/>eſt vna omnium perixtio,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> there is made a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all creatures together; the Angels ioyne company with men, in praiſing God on earth, as it fell out when Chriſt was borne: and men are added to the quiers of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels in heauen, as it comes to paſſe when a Chriſtian dies.</p>
            <p>For our outward eſtate, they waite on vs, as if they were more ours then their owne.<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.10.</note> See, ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>that yee deſpiſe not one of theſe little ones, for I ſay vnto you, their Angels doe alwaies behold the face of my father which is in heauen.</hi> Mat. 18.10. Iuſtly he ſaith, their Angels, for they are,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirits, ſent out for their good, which ſhall be heires of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. Not that we are able certainely to determine, that euery one hath his owne Angell<note n="c" place="margin">Specialiter defigna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Lomb. lib. 2. diſtinc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Rhem. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Mat. 18.10.</note> ſpecially allotted vnto him, as they of <hi>Rome</hi> teach: but that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Angels are appointed vnto one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25090:13"/>ſuruant, if neceſſitie require; as the ſcriptures of god teach.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 91.13.</note> Pſal. 91.13. They ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinell alway by vs, and pitch their tents about vs.<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. And the more herein is ſhewed Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to vs, the more hereby ſhould be manifeſted our confidence in him. <hi>He hath giuen his Angels charge ouer thee</hi> ſaith <hi>the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Bern. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Quihabitat. verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam tibi debet hoc verbum inferre reuerentiam, afferre deuotionem, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre fiduciam?</hi> This ſweet word of his, ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi> how great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſhould it ſtrike, how great deuotion breed, how great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence kindle? Reuerence for the prefence of the Angels, deuotion for their beneuolence, confidence for their cuſtodie.<note n="g" place="margin">Bern. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Caute ambula,</hi> walke warily, the Angels of God are preſent with thee, when all men on earth are abſent from thee: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not to doe that in the ſight of an heauenly Angel, which thou wouldſt ſhame to doe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25090:13"/>of an earthly man. And thus much touching the firſt perſon.</p>
            <p>The ſecond perſons are the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which ſeeke. Now who they were in particular, none of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts in my iudgement haue ſo fully ſet downe, as this our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt S. <hi>Marke;</hi> For he, verſ 1. of this chapter, hath ſet downe their number, and their names. Their number <hi>three.</hi> Their names, <hi>Marie Magdalen, Marie the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Iames,</hi> and <hi>Salome;</hi> Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo with the ende of their comming, and the time of it. The ende, <hi>to embalme the dead bodie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> The time, <hi>verie early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning while the Sunne was riſing.</hi> Verie forward deuotion indeed, you will ſay, ſo ſoone to be ſtirring, but what might moue them hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? Some peraduenture will ſay, pittie of the dead corps. For wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haue this nature, when en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie cannot moue them, pittie will driue them. When the ioy of his life could not bring them to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25090:14"/>his loue, the ſorrow of his death did fetch them to his graue. Some againe, happily may ſay: Deſire of newes. For women like the men of <hi>Athens,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.21.</note> 
               <hi>giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues wholy, either to heare, or to tell ſome newes.</hi> Act. 17.21. So they, which were wearie of his ſight while he was aliue, did now long after it, when he was dead. But God forbid, ſo charitable creatures ſhould euer vndergoe ſo vncharitable a cenſure. I ſay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it was loue, it was pietie, it was decencie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it was loue; For<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.47.</note> 
               <hi>He loueth much, to whom much is forgiuen.</hi> Luk. 7.47. But Chriſt, not only forgaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much, but gaue them much.<note n="k" place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cant. Ser. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Dilectionem non reddidit, fed addidit, ſaith Bern:</hi> He returned not loue as a debt, but beſtowed it as a gift. And therefore if you maruell why thus they loued him, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwereth for himſelfe, and them alſo,<note n="l" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>We loue him becauſe he loued vs firſt.</hi> 1. Ioh. 4.19. Hereunto
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25090:14"/>adde, that beſide his generall loue wherewith he loued them as his elect, he alſo affected them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular loue as his friends. One of them, <hi>Marie Iacobi,</hi> was his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſiſter; and his loue was not wanting, either to her, or her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Not to her ſelfe, he made her his Aunt. Not to her children; For, of her fower ſonnes, <hi>Iames, Ioſes. Simon, Iude,</hi> he choſe two, the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and the youngeſt to be his holy Apoſtles. A fauour ſo great, and a priuiledge ſo high, that if he had made them Monarches, it had come ſhort of this. But to <hi>Marie Magdalen</hi> he ſhewed more loue, and ſo much the more appeares it, for that, ſhe was not of his kinred. She neuer wanted either his good deeds to comfort her, or his good words to excuſe her. Not his good deeds for her comfort, either for her ſelfe or her friends. Not for her ſelfe.<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.3.</note> Out of her he caſt ſeauen diuels. <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.3. Not for her
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25090:15"/>friends.<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.44.</note> Her brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> he raiſed from dead. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.44.<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.38.</note> Her ſiſter <hi>Martha</hi> he graced with his preſence, and preaching in her houſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.38. As ſhe had his good deeds, ſo had ſhe alwaies his good words. For he excuſed her three times. Firſt, to the Phariſee, <hi>who ſaid ſhe was a ſinner.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lu.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 39</note> Luk. 7.39. Secondly, to her ſiſter, <hi>who ſaid ſhe was idle.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.41.</note> Thirdly, to <hi>Iudas,</hi> who ſaid ſhe was <hi>prodigall.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.10.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.10. What could Chriſt doe more for them, while he was aliue, or they leſſe for Chriſt now he was dead?</p>
            <p>Secondly, it was pietie, wherein they exceeded men. For as they ſhewed more ſorrow then men at Chriſts paſſion: ſo they ſhewed more deuotion then men at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Whilſt then men were ſecurely ſleeping in the nightly graue of their beds, theſe deuout women were religiouſly ſeeking Chriſt in the quiet bed of his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25090:15"/>graue. They feared not the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, which might haue produced dangerous effects: they reſpected not the malice of the Iewes, which hated ſuch as lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Chriſt: they ſhrunke not at the horror of the dead corpes, which is a thing that fleſh trembles at <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they were not daunted at their owne weakeneſſe, the ſtouteſt of them being but a woman, <hi>mulier, mollis aer,</hi> a ſoft and tender breath, <hi>faemina, ferens minus,</hi> leaſt able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and hold out: not any of theſe, not all of them could hold them backe from ſeeking of <hi>him whom their ſoule loued.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1.</note> Cant. 3.1. Loe here deare Chriſtians, moſt deuout charitie, moſt charitable deuotion. Loe, how true it is, that women, as by nature they paralell men in wit; ſo by grace they equall them in vertue. What can you ſay againſt them? If one were a cauſe of death, another was a meanes of life. One indeed, receiued, t <hi>verbum
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25090:16"/>adificatorium mor<note n="t" place="margin">Tenull. lib. de came Chriſti.</note> is,</hi> the word that ſet vp death; but another concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>verbum extructorium vitae,</hi> the word which ſet vp life againe. One beleeued the diuell, and another gaue credit to the Angel,<note n="u" place="margin">Tertull. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Ei quod illa credendo deliquit, haec credendo deleuit,</hi> what the firſt by raſh cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting loſt, the other by true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing got againe.<note n="x" place="margin">Verbum diaboli ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men illi fuit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt One by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing denique dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricidam. Contra Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eum edidit, qui carnalem fratrem Iſrael, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorem ſuum, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaret Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. ibid.</note> the diuell, brought forth a murtherer that ſlew his brother in the field; the other, by beleeuing God, broght forth a Sauiour ſlaine by his brethren in the fleſh. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Eue</hi> ſignifieth life, and <hi>Marie</hi> importeth bitterneſſe, but they were both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to their names: for <hi>Eue</hi> in ſtead of life, brought death: and <hi>Marie</hi> in ſteed of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, brought ſweetnes.</p>
            <p>Now, theſe women were the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters and proclaimers of this benefite. The gloriouſeſt meſſage that euer was, was firſt committed to a woman, becauſe the woman
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:25090:16"/>firſt haſted to heare it. As <hi>Marie</hi> was the meane betweene God and man to beare Chriſt, and bring meanes of ſaluation; ſo theſe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were the meane betweene the Angell and men, to preach Chriſt, and bring newes of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As there was a progreſſe in the denunciation of death, from the diuell to the woman, from the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the man: ſo, there was a proceſſe in the anunciation of life, from the Angell to the women, from the women vnto men. For,<note n="a" place="margin">Miſſae ab angelo, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus faciant Evangeli. ſiae, facta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Apoſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, feſtiuantad annuncian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum mane miſeritor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cant. Ser. 75.</note> ſent from a Angell, they doe the worke of an Euangeliſt, and being made Apoſtles, to the Apoſtles, they goe forth with ſpeed, to ſing the mercies of the Lord, betimes in the morning.<note n="b" place="margin">Quae pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma iuit ad culpam, nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e prima currit ad veniam Ludolp. de vit. Chri. patt. 2. cap. 71.</note> The woman therefore which firſt fell to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, doth now firſt fell to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, doth now firſt bring newes of remiſſion; and ſhe which at firſt brought death into para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, doth now firſt of all fetch life from the ſepulchre,<note n="c" place="margin">Id ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Contenders
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25090:17"/>de morte rapere vitam, quae offendens de vita rapuit mortem,</hi> contending, ſaith one, out of death to fetch life, which before offending out of life did bring death.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it was decencie. Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, two waies. Firſt, naturally, which allowes it neither for cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, nor commendable, for ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trons to goe alone. And indeed, in ſo heauy a caſe as death, at ſo vnwo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſeaſon as night, to ſo diſmall a place as the graue, if they had gone ſingle, they might haue fainted, and fallen,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>vaſoli,</hi> ſaith the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Woe be to him that is alone,</hi> eſpecially, if he be alone in his woe. Therefore, as all had loſt, ſo all ſought, and happily, &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, all found. Secondly, ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which required, that amidſt ſo many enemies of the reſurrection, ſufficient witneſſe ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, to confirme the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now the ſcripture ſaith,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 19.15.</note> 
               <hi>in the mouth of two or three witneſſes, euery
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25090:17"/>word ſhall ſtand.</hi> Deu 19.15. Two then might haue ſerued, but here were three, and<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>a three-fold cord is not eaſily broken.</hi> Eccle. 4 12.</p>
            <p>In a word then, As deuotion ſtirred vp theſe women to ſeeke, and finding, incouraged their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion: ſo let precept moue vs to be deuout, that practiſe may bring vs to the like bleſſed finding. A firſt we all ſhamed not to imitate woman in following the diuell to damnation: let vs now much leſſe ſhame to imitate theſe women, in running to Chriſt for ſaluation. Though they be women, their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample is notable. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe at their word, ran out. <hi>Iohn,</hi> not onely runnes out with <hi>Peter.</hi> but<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.4</note> 
               <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runnes him.</hi> Ioh. 20.4. <hi>Peter</hi> hath his name from <hi>Petra.</hi> a rocke, and yet he relented at the loue of Chriſt: but<note n="h" place="margin">O graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores ſaxo &amp; plumbo, quos ta ti a noris vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum, non t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bit f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ex quo prins t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it deum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme. lib. de ſimil.</note> 
               <hi>Oh harder and heauier than ſtone, and lead, are their hearts,</hi> ſaith Anſelme, <hi>who are not drawne from earth, to loue God in heauen, by that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25090:18"/>band, which drew God out of heauen,</hi> to loue man on earth The graue of Chriſt is our hiding place. As the beaſtes that are hunted by men, flie into dennes and holes of the earth, for ſafetie againſt the furie of dogges: ſo let vs, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like the beaſtes that periſh, when we are hunted by Sathan, that mightie Nimrod, flie, &amp; hide our ſelues in the graue of Chriſt. There and no where elſe,<note n="i" place="margin">Et Reuera, vb firma tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eſt, oiſi i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vulucri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Saluato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris? Bern: ſuper Cant. Serm.</note> is firme and ſafe ſecuritie to be found. It is his promiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; <hi>he will not ſhrinke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it.</hi> Trie him, O feeble ſoule, in thy greateſt need,<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.3.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhall preſerue thee from the ſnare of the hunter.</hi> Pſ. 91.3. Thus much, touching the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The matter follows, &amp; firſt, of the Angells conſolation, <hi>Be not afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the firſt hearing whereof, peraduenture ſome may be afraid, that it is not the voice of a good Angell from heauen, it ſounds ſo like the rotten ſtay of ſecuritie, which the Diuell gaue our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:25090:18"/>to reſt on earth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not die at all.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> Gen. 3.5. For, doth not the Scripture by precept commaund <hi>Feare?</hi> Do not all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie men by practiſe commend it? Was it not at firſt created and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a qualitie in the ſoule of man? Was it not afterwardes an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſoule of him which was both God &amp; man? Hearken deare Chriſtians: He ſaith not, <hi>Feare not at all:</hi> but he meaneth,<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ne auonito ſtupore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreamini.</note> 
               <hi>Feare not too much.</hi> And indeed, in this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, great diſcretion is to be vſed. Therefore, the ſcripture ſometime ſaith <hi>Feare:</hi> ſometimes againe, <hi>Be not afraid. Feare,</hi> for too little feare, is want of grace. <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> too much feare is want of faith. <hi>Feare,</hi> too little feare is preſumption. <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> too much feare is deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this very precept, <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> inſtructs vs in three points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, who it is that ought to be feared. Not men, not Angells, not diuels, but God only. The ſeruant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25090:19"/>feares not his fellowes in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, but<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6</note> Mal. 1.6 God is <hi>Paterfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milias,</hi> maiſter of the familie, and the Angells be<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22 9</note> 
               <hi>our fellow ſeruants.</hi> Reu 22 9. Againe, whom we muſt worſhip, him muſt wee feare; for feare is a ſpeciall part of Gods worſhip. But,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 4 10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou muſt worſhip the Lord thy God onely, and him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſerue.</hi> Matth. 4.10. Therefore the Lord God muſt onely be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Secondly, who it is, that ought to feare. Not ſuch as<note n="q" place="margin">Cuſtodes quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> digni ſunt qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntur, vos autem diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipulae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, ne ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mini. The op. in Mat. 8.</note> ſeek Chriſt, like theſe bleſſed women, but ſuch as kill Chriſt, like the curſed <hi>Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As there is a twofold compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men; that is, of pride, and humilitie: ſo there is double diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in God, of Iuſtice, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. He, which is<note n="r" place="margin">Lactant. Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>erg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pios, indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiſſimus Pater,</hi> a moſt louing and gentle Father to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; the ſame is alſo <hi>aduerſus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios rectiſſimus iudex:</hi> A moſt ſeuere
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25090:19"/>and iuſt iudge to the wicked. And heere, the verſe ſame God by his Angel, ſo frighted the wicked kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Chriſt,<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.4</note> that they became like dead men, <hi>Mat..</hi> 28.4. But yet, ſo cheered of theſe bleſſed ſeekers of Chriſt, that he expelled all feare from them, ſaying: <hi>Be not afraid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how it is that we ought to feare. For there is one <hi>Feare,</hi> which,<note n="t" place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.18</note> perfect loue caſteth out. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.18. And another <hi>feare,</hi> which<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 15 33.</note> 
               <hi>bringeth in the loue of God.</hi> Pro. 15.33. This wee muſt embrace, not that. This, becauſe it is like the feare of a louing wife, which<note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>19</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quo quanto ardentius diligit, tanto diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius cauet offendere,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine:</hi> The more ardently ſhee loues her husband, the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſhe takes heed of offending him. Therefore, <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth it<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.9</note> 
               <hi>Caſtus timor,</hi> Pſ. 19.9. <hi>Chaſt feare,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 19. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gratis amans</hi> ſaith Auguſtine, <hi>non puniri timens ab eo, quem tremit, ſed ſeparari ab eo quem diligit.</hi> Louing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:25090:20"/>freely, and fearing louingly, not ſo much, leaſt ſhe be puniſhed of him whom ſhe dreades, as leaſt ſhe be diuided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him whom ſhe loues.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that by <hi>Feare</hi> is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified all Gods worſhip &amp; ſeruice. <hi>Dauid</hi> calling to all Gods ſeruants, intituleth them,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16</note> 
               <hi>ſuch as feare God,</hi> Pſalm. 66.16. <hi>Abraham</hi> when hee would ſignifie <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and his ſeruants to be without religion, ſaid,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.11</note> 
               <hi>Surely, I thought the feare of God was not in this place.</hi> Gen. 20.11.11. When <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> made a couenant, <hi>Laban</hi> ſware by his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.54</note> 
               <hi>but Iacob ſware by the Feare of his father Iſaac.</hi> Geneſ. 31.54. So true it is, that one ſaith, <hi>Vbi non eſt metus non eſt religio.</hi> Where feare is wanting, Religion is abſent. And<note n="f" place="margin">Tertul. li. de penitent.</note> 
               <hi>Timor hominis Dei honor eſt.</hi> Mans feare is Gods honour.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe, Feare is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Porter. A good Porter will keepe out rogues and varlets out of his Lords houſe: ſo doth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25090:20"/>
               <hi>Feare</hi> thruſt vices out of the ſoule.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>The feare of the Lord driueth out ſinne.</hi> Eccl. 1.26. Herein, it is like to <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> which ſignifieth the fire of the Lord. Hee put downe the high places, cut down the groues, demoliſhed <hi>Baals</hi> altars, ſacrificed his Prieſts, and like a fire, burned and conſumed all the peoples ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations.<note n="h" place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 23.5.</note> 2. Kings. 23.5. So Feare, like a ſpirituall fire, both burnes vp our ſtubble of vitious qualities, and warmes the heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly with a zeale of Gods glory: and like the good huſwife, ſweeps cleane our heart, that it may be an holy Temple for the Lord.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>A good Porter will let in all his Lords friendes, that his houſe may be furniſhed with gueſts.</hi> So doth <hi>Feare,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1.21</note> 
               <hi>Shee filleth her houſe with al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things deſireable,</hi> Eccl. 1.21. And therefore, when <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſome worthie matter to relate, he choſe for his auditors<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.16</note> 
               <hi>Such as feare God.</hi> Pſal. 66.16.<note n="l" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 65. Dei timor aperiat au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vt ſit quod intret, &amp; qua in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tret Aug. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt quibus narre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25090:21"/>ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, vbs Dei ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor non eſt</hi> Where <hi>feare</hi> hath made no paſſage, there wordes can haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o entrance: but let feare once open the eare, and there will be matter to enter, and entrance for matter. To conclude, <hi>A good Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er will retaine vigilancie:</hi> for feare <hi>the thiefe enter in, &amp; ſpoyle the houſe.</hi> So true <hi>Feare</hi> euer wakes, leaſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule by negligence be betrayed. For<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 27 3</note> 
               <hi>if a man holde him not ſure in the Feare of the Lord, his houſe will ſoone be ouerthrowne,</hi> Eccleſ. 27.3. Hence Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Hieron. ad Fabiolam.</note> 
               <hi>Timor vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utum custos eſt, Securitas ad lapſum facilis.</hi> Feare is vertues Guardian, whilſt ſecuritie makes ſhipwracke of goodnes.</p>
            <p>With this feare then, let vs feare <hi>alwayes,</hi> for it is the part of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, at any time to want it: I ſay, at any time. For<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.14</note> 
               <hi>He is bleſſed that feareth alwayes.</hi> Prou. 28.14. Not, that feareth <hi>ſometime,</hi> but <hi>alwayes.</hi> There be three eſtates of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25090:21"/>in this life, and <hi>Feare</hi> muſt be wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting to none of them.<note place="margin">Time cum ariſent gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratia time cum abierit, time cum denuo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertetur. Bern ſuper Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. ſer. 54.</note> There is the eſtate of <hi>grace,</hi> the eſtate of a <hi>lapſe</hi> &amp; the eſtate of <hi>recouery.</hi> In the eſtate of <hi>grace,</hi> we muſt feare God, for his goodnes.<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 20</note> 
               <hi>Through vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe they are broken off and thou ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt faſt by faith. Be not high minded, but Feare.</hi> Ro. 11.20. In the eſtate of a <hi>lapſe,</hi> God muſt be feared, for his Iuſtice.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.40</note> 
               <hi>Feareſt not thou, ſeeing thou art in the estate of condemnation?</hi> Luk. 23.40. In the eſtate of <hi>reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie,</hi> wee muſt feare God for his mercie.<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130 4</note> 
               <hi>If thou marke our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who may abide it? but there is mercie with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared.</hi> Pſal. 130.4. In the eſtate of <hi>grace,</hi> Feare, ſaith <hi>Bern</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Bern ſuper Cantic. ſer 54.</note> 
               <hi>ne non dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne opereris ex ea:</hi> Leaſt thou turne grace into wantonnes.<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.18</note> Leaſt thou be like the ſloathfull ſeruant, that buried his talent in a napkin. <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.18. Doeſt thou not burie thy talent, when thou haſt learning and riches, and yet helpeſt neither
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25090:22"/>the poore, nor the ignorant? Or leaſt thou be like the vniuſt Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.1.</note> 
               <hi>who was accuſed to his maiſter, that hee had waſted his goods.</hi> Luc. 16.1. Do we not waſt Gods goods, when gifts are giuen vs to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie withall, and wee gaine nothing by them, either to our ſelues or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Againe, in the eſtate of a lapſe: <hi>Feare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Bern: vt ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Quia dereliquit te cuſtodia tua:</hi> Becauſe thy Guardian hath left thee. Thou art expoſed like a young <hi>Moyſes,</hi> to the mercies of the vnſatiable gulfe. The good Spirit hath left thee, and thou art in the hands of an euill vexing ſpirit. If thy ſtate be not to be feared, what is? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in the eſtate of <hi>recouerie. Feare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Quia recidere, quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidere eſt deterius.</hi> The ſecond fall, is worſe then the firſt.<note n="z" place="margin">Repudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am &amp; nam &amp; mari, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt. Tert. de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</note> Many that haue made ſhipwracke of goods, bid ſhippe and Sea farewell: how much more ſhould a man feare a ſecond ſhipwracke of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25090:22"/>Say God hath pardoned thee once: Say twice: Say many times, wilt thou <hi>continue in ſinne, that grace may abound? God forbid.</hi> No reaſon, ſaith <hi>I ertullian,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nemo id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circo dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quia deus melior eſt. Ibid.</note> that man ſhould be worſe, becauſe God is better, <hi>&amp; redundantia clementiae caeleſtis, libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m faciat humanae temeritatis,</hi> and the abundance of heauenlie bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence, ſhould bring forth ſtore of preſumptuous impudencie. Say not of thy ſinnes, as the drunkard of his wines,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.25.</note> 
               <hi>They haue ſmitten me, but I was not ſicke, therefore will I ſeeke it yet ſtill.</hi> Pro. 23.25. Rather,<note n="c" place="margin">Dei bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſuam ſcilicet, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Tert. lib de poe.</note> honour Gods benefites, with the memorie of thy perill, and ſay, My former danger ſhalbe an afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I haue bene <hi>praemonitus,</hi> I will now be <hi>praemunitus,</hi> once forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; euer after forearmed. And thus much touching the Angells conſolation.</p>
            <p>The next point, is the womens inquiſition, in theſe words, <hi>ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:25090:23"/>
And this depends on the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, as a reaſon of it. <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> ſaith he. Why? <hi>Becauſe ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was crucified.</hi> Indeed, they which ſeeke <hi>Christ, and him crucified,</hi> haue no reaſon to feare anie thing, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if they find what they ſeeke. But they muſt goe through to <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> or elſe, their comfort is miſerable, and their ſeeking of no value. For in this inquiſition, there are foure degrees, and all good, if they tend to Chriſt crucified, but none good, if they bend not thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. To make this apparant, I will relate the comfort, and inferre the obiection <hi>Be not afraid,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>For ye ſeeke.</hi> There is one degree. Indeed the ſcripture commaunds vs to <hi>ſeeke,</hi> but it is <hi>the kingdome of God:</hi> and maine ſeeke, but fewe <hi>the kingdome of God;</hi> therefore one may <hi>ſeeke,</hi> and yet iuſtly <hi>he afraid.</hi> He replieth againe. <hi>Be not afraid, yee ſeeke Ieſus.</hi> A ſecond degree,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25090:23"/>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 1.21</note>
               <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſignifieth a Sauiour, and he that findes the true <hi>Ieſus,</hi> findeth the true ſaluation: but euery <hi>Ieſus</hi> is not a Sauiour; therefore one may ſeeke <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and yet iuſtlie <hi>be afraid.</hi> He addeth in the next place, <hi>Be not afraid, ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. A third degree, <hi>Nazaret</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth a flower: and he that findes the true <hi>Nazarite,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 11.1.</note> findes <hi>the true Flower of Ieſſe.</hi> But as euery <hi>Ieſus</hi> is not a Sauiour, ſo euery <hi>Nazarite</hi> is not a flower: therefore, one may <hi>ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, &amp; yet iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>be afraid.</hi> The Angel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludes, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not afraid, ye ſeeke Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>which was crucified.</hi> The fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, the degree of <hi>perfection:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which, nothing can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, to make a man iuſtly <hi>afraid.</hi> For more inſtance in theſe points. To <hi>ſeeke,</hi> abſolutely, is not good, but onely ſo farre forth, as it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Croſſe. True it is, in this world wee are all at a loſſe, and can neuer finde what we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25090:24"/>loſt, till we be found of him, <hi>Who came to ſeeke, and to ſaue that which was loſt.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.10</note> Lu 19.10. As all ſeeking is vaine, vnles we ſeeke him; ſo all ſeeking of him is in vaine, vnles he finde vs: and hee muſt be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for both, ſaith <hi>Fulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Siue cum nos ad ſe quaerendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dormientes exſuſcitat, ſeu cum ſe inueniendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obis quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Falg. ad monim. li. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be for ſtirring vs vp to ſeeke him, when we are ſleeping, or for offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe vnto vs, when we are ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</hi> Hee that ſeekes other thing then this, or otherwiſe then thus, ſhalbe ſure to looſe, as the prouerb ſaith, <hi>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ram &amp; oleum:</hi> both his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in ſeeking, and his coſt in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.6</note> This way onely, ſeeking is good, and ſeekers gainers. <hi>This is the generation of them that ſeeke thee, euen of them that ſeeke thy face.</hi> Pſal. 24.6. All other ſeeking is vaine, and finders, loſers; Of which there are manie generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the world, and of whome <hi>Paul</hi> complaineth, ſaying:<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>All ſeeke their owne, &amp; not that which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Phil. 2.21.</p>
            <p>For example.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:25090:24"/>
Some ſeeke their owne wealth and riches. Say I ſome? I may ſay, All: for it is that which we ſeek for, both All and Some.<note n="k" place="margin">O ciues, ciues quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renda pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia primum eſt, virtus poſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos Haec Ianos ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ab imo per docet &amp;c. Hor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſt. 1.</note> Citizens giue eare to ſuch as ſpeake from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niple of <hi>lanus, Quaeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da pecunia primum eſt.</hi> Seeke money aboue all things; rather then to ſuch as exhort them in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>IESVS,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 6.33</note> 
               <hi>Quaerite primum r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnum D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i; Seeke firſt the kingdome of GOD, and then all theſe things ſhalbe minittred vnto you.</hi> Mat. 6.33. Hence it comes to paſſe, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them which be rich to the world, are very poore to God. For 2. heauy burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> inuade the rich mans thoughtes.<note n="m" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. hom. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Deliciarum putredo, curarum mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo:</hi> the vanitie of fleſhlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and the greatnes of worldlie cares:<note n="n" place="margin">Quorum vnum quod que ad ſubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigium ſuf. ficit. Ibid.</note> of which, the leaſt is able to ſinke a ſhippe. Hence <hi>Chriſt</hi> compareth a rich man to a Camel,<note n="o" place="margin">Ambro. Serm 4. Ille o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bus, iſte peccatis</note> 
               <hi>vter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habet propria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſarcinam,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> They haue each of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:25090:25"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on their backs, the one of fleſh, the other, of fleſhly luſts. Not that <hi>riches</hi> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are euil but the immoderate loue <hi>of riches; Paul</hi> ſaith not, <hi>They which are rich,</hi> but <hi>they which will be rich, fall into temptation,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.9</note> 1. Tim. 6.9. <hi>In diuitijs cupiditate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprehendit, non facultate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith S.<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt: de ciuit. dei, lib. 1. cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> Reprehending indeed, the wretchedneſſe of the mind, not the richnes of the man.</p>
            <p>Some ſeeke for vaine-glorie. An intollerable drunkenneſſe of the mind, ſaith Saint<note n="r" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Ioh. ho. 2</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and ſuch a diſeaſe, as is not eaſilie cured. Into this ranke of ſeekers, I may put (as I feare mee) ſome of our brethren; or rather (for which I grieue) they haue put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Who, as ſome olde Monkes were wont to be proud of humilitie; ſo theſe men ſtriue to be accounted moſt learned, by ſhewing no lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. We with our learning may ſift while wee will into the deepeſt queſtions, but <hi>all the Flowre.</hi> they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25090:25"/>ſay, <hi>is of their boulting.</hi> Great Clerks with their learned preaching, doe nothing: our their ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is the onely mother to breed and bring forth deuotion. When we alledge a Father, they ſay, wee preach our ſelues, whilſt they, being as much beholding to them as wee, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their names, father all vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. Me thinks I may applie <hi>Iobs</hi> words vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thogh they haue not halfe the eloquence of <hi>Iobs friends:</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.2</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ye onely are the people, learning muſt die with you.</hi> Iob. 12.2. For they are the onely people now a dayes, and onely the peoples; to whome they ſuggeſt, that like new <hi>Palaemons, ſecum natae, &amp; periturae literae;</hi> learning hath her birth, &amp; her death with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe they are the peoples, they willingly permit all learning to die wth them, becauſe they ſee, that learning &amp; the peoples loue, no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dagon</hi> &amp; the <hi>Ark</hi> can ſtand together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:25090:26"/>
And <hi>certes</hi> in my iudgment, this is the time of fufilling that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, which Almightie God ſaid ſhould come to paſſe ſome time;<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.2</note> 
               <hi>Like people, like prieſt,</hi> Iſay. 24.2. It could not be ſo ſaid in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church: then the Prieſt was better then the people: nor was it verified in the time of Poperie, as <hi>Bern.</hi> doth witneſſe, <hi>Non poteſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ici, vt eſt populus, ita eſt Sacerdos, quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am non ita eſt populus vt Sacerdos.</hi> It cannot be ſaid, As is the people, ſo is the Prieſt, becauſe the people is not ſo bad as the Prieſt. But now, now it ſeemes, is the time come, that the people &amp; the prieſt are both alike, whilſt the one for fancy, will heare nothing but what hee liſt; the other for aduantage, will ſpeake nothing, but what may pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Some ſeeke for Honour, for which their ſoule gapeth, as much as the thirſtie land for raine, in the drought of Sommer: and ſo faſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25090:26"/>hath Ambition ſeized on their ſoules that they growe proud of Honour before they haue it. And ſure it is an euill which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanieth preferment, that whereas it ſhuld make a man more humble, and ſo more truely hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">Auguſt. de Temp. Serm. 213.</note> 
               <hi>Honoris laus, humilitatis virtus:</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of true honour, is the vertue of humilitie:) yet men for the moſt part, then growe proud and arrogant. Yea, and let me vſe Saint <hi>Bern:</hi> words,<note n="x" place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s eſt, hom. 4</note> 
               <hi>Si audeo dicere,</hi> If I durſt be ſo bold as to tell them of it, Me thinks I ſee ſome, <hi>quod ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epti ſunt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mis, attribuere meritis:</hi> to impute that to their <hi>good deſeruings,</hi> which they haue bought and payd for, with their full purſes. Not that Honour is any way euill in it ſelfe,<note n="y" place="margin">Auguſt. de ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. Serm. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Bonum eſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, ſed hoc, ſi bene vtatis.</hi> It is a thing good enough, if thou vſeſt it well; yea a ſpeciall good, if directed to the right end. If thou vſeſt it well,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25090:27"/>it will be<note n="z" place="margin">Auguſt. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſterium boni operis,</hi> an oportunitie to doe manie good deedes: if ill, it will prooue, <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio exitij:</hi> a meanes of a heauier iudgement, when the mightie ſhall be mightily tormented.</p>
            <p>Some ſeeke for pride: A ſinne hatched by the Diuell at the firſt, and harboured ſince by diuells in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate: yet, ſo common among vs, that what onely we ſhuld yeeld to vertue, we frankly beſtow on it, emulation.</p>
            <p>Some, becauſe they would be beyond emulation, ſo paint their bodies with ſtrange garments, and ſtaine their faces with painted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions, that they grow out of the ranke of humane creatures, &amp;<note n="a" place="margin">Idola me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuntur. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</note> are becom very <hi>Idolls.</hi> And that which no man durſt doe to the picture of an earthly Prince, ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Chryſoſt: in Matth. hom. 31.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſ.</hi> they preſume to do, to the image of the <hi>K. of kings.</hi> Doſt thou thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k thou art a better work man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God: Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy painting adds to thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25090:27"/>yet it taketh away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe; &amp; in the freſheſt of thy ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard beautie, thou art but<note n="c" place="margin">Hieron: ad Marcell.</note> 
               <hi>nimio candore deformis:</hi> deformed with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch faireneſſe.</p>
            <p>But if Gods commaundement could preuaile nothing, yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes Women ſhould feare to paint, leaſt men ſhould point at them, for the <hi>Hieroglyphicke</hi> of an hypocrite. For the hypocrits pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, ſaith <hi>Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Lactant: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtit. lib. 3. cap. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Non excindere vitia, ſed abſcondere:</hi> not to race vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces quite out, but only to couer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a vaile: or as <hi>Bernard</hi> more ſignificantly hath it,<note n="e" place="margin">Bern: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cant: Serm: 66.</note> 
               <hi>Virtutes non colere, ſed vitia colocare:</hi> not to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace vertue with a good inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, but to paint ouer vice, with a faire complexion.</p>
            <p>Some ſeek for pleaſure:<note n="f" place="margin">Volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tas malorum eſca.</note> Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the nouriſhment of all vices.<note n="g" place="margin">Dum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, illudit.</note> The wilie Paraſite of the wanton fleſh, deceiuing throughly, while it ſporteth merilie.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="h" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>an at.</note>The <hi>Syren</hi> of the ſoule, ſtinging
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25090:28"/>deepely, while it ſingeth ſweetely.<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 10.10</note> Like the book which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> eate which was in his mouth as ſweet as honie, and in his bellie as bitter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaul. And like vnto the ſubtile har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.3.4. <hi>Whoſe lips at the firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drop as an home combe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">k <hi>Pro.</hi> 5.3.4</note> 
               <hi>but her latte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> end is bitter as wormewood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſeeke for reuenge. And of late wee haue ſeene, euen vnto ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grief, ſome tragedies which it hath brought forth, whiſſt they whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſought it, haue found, not ſo much reuenge vpon others, as vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to themſelues. For reuenge is on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe 3. things which God hath reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rued to himſelfe. His glorie is the firſt:<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> 
               <hi>My glorie I will not giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o another.</hi> Iſa. 42.8. Iudgment is the next.<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is one L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-giuer, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is able to ſaue &amp; to destroy: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> art thou that iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt another?</hi> Iam. 4.12. And the third is reuenge.<note n="n" place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce is mine, &amp; I will repay it.</hi> Deut. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.35. What a lamentable thing then is it, that now adayes a man
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25090:28"/>cannot be accounted rightly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, vnleſſe he prooue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe deſperately vicious?<note n="o" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari vis Chriſtiana,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> Art thou a Chriſtian, and wilt be reuenged? Tarrie a while, <hi>Nondum vindicatus eſt Christus;</hi> Thy Lord and maiſter Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, is not yet reuenged of his owne death. I cannot tarrie, ſaith the hote ſpirit, nay I cannot liue to beare this diſgrace, without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall obliquie. But ô inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate furie, how it hath gained an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of magnanimitie!</p>
            <p>Some there be, which imagine this timerous reſolution, to be the ſpirit of true valour: but indeed it is far otherwiſe, and nothing elſe, but the infirmitie of the fleſh. For true magnanimity begins at home, and ſubdues it's owne paſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p Auguſt. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. dei: lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. 23. Ex velle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Pater ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c.</note> becauſe hee would not be vanquiſhed by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> k drew out his own ſword, &amp; ſlue himſelfe at <hi>Vtica.</hi> Some may think this great valour
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:25090:29"/>too, but what ſaith S. <hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. vt ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Non fuit honestas turpia praecauens, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed infirmitas aduerſa non ſuſtinens:</hi> It was no honeſt minde to auoid after diſgraces, but a weakenes that could not indure former wrongs. And this is the beſt which may be thought of the boldnes of ſingle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>batters, to omit the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous hazard of their ſoules, in ſo bloodie a manner forſaking their bodies. Thus then, whilſt the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen ſeekes for wealth, the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for popularities, the ambitious man for honour, the Courtier for pride, the laſciuious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the gallant for reuenge, it is come to paſſe, as <hi>Paul</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth, t <hi>All ſeeke their owne, and not that which is Ieſus Chriſts.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil</hi> 2.21.</note> and as <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 14.2.</note> 
               <hi>There is none that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth, and ſeeketh after God.</hi> Pſal. 14.2.</p>
            <p>Come we to the ſecond degree; <hi>Yee ſeebe Ieſus.</hi> Neither doth this commend abſolutely, becauſe ſo
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25090:29"/>many ſeek him diſſolutely. For it is certaine, ſome corruptly ſeek the true <hi>Ieſus;</hi> Some carefully purſue a falſe <hi>Ieſus.</hi> While the true <hi>Ieſus</hi> was on earth, ſome ſought him cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly, <hi>viz.</hi> for the cure of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſauing of their ſoules; to behold his miracles, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to admire his vertues; to fill their mouths with bread, rather then their hearts with faith: and to catch him in his words, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be catched by his word. The 9. <hi>leapers</hi> cried after him to be cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, but neuer returnd <hi>to giue him tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 17.17.</note> 
               <hi>Herode</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lu.</hi> 23.8.</note> 
               <hi>deſired to ſee a miracle,</hi> &amp; preſently ſent him back to <hi>Pilate</hi> to be crucified. Luc. 23.8. The <hi>Capernaits</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.60</note> 
               <hi>eat of the loaues, &amp; were filled</hi> &amp; afterwards murmured and forſooke him. Ioh 6.60. The <hi>Phariſies</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> had all their queſtions anſwered, and then<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.5.</note> 
               <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered a Councell to put him to death.</hi> Matth. 26.3. Thus the true <hi>Ieſus</hi> was corruptly ſought.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:25090:30"/>
That <hi>Ieſus</hi> which holy <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith, is,<note n="z" place="margin">Igna. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist: ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> 
               <hi>vita fidelium,</hi> life to the faithfull in the bittereſt death: and which, as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, is<note n="a" place="margin">Bern: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Canuc. Ser. 15.</note> 
               <hi>mel in ore, in aure melos, in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de iubilus;</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie in the mouth, melodie in the eare, ioy and ioniſance in the hart, ſought after for corrupt and ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter reſpects, no whit profiteth the greedie ſeekers.</p>
            <p>Some againe carefully purſue a falſe <hi>Ieſus.</hi> propoſing to their minde, ſafetie in that thing which they moſt affect, and repoſing in their hearts a confidence therein. Yea, almoſt euery kingdome in the world, almoſt euery citie in a kingdome, almoſt euery man in a citie, hath a falſe <hi>Ieſus,</hi> in whom he delighteth, and in whom he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely reſtes. The Turkes <hi>Ieſus</hi> is their brainſicke prophet <hi>Mahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> in him they place their faith, of him they hope for ſaluation. To his bountie, they impute the largeneſſe of their empire, the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25090:30"/>of their ſoile, and to his right hand,<note n="b" place="margin">Lactan. Inſtitut. lib. 2. cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>quicquid eſt, propter quod fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; latrocinia, &amp; homicidia quotidie ſaeuiunt:</hi> whatſoeuer it is, for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing whereof, thefts, robberies, &amp; murders are euery day among them outragious, and whole cities and townes ouerthrowne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed, as <hi>Lacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> once ſaid of the ſuperſtitious heathen. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts <hi>Ieſus</hi> is the Pope; For of him they expect all, which is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be receiued from the true <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Nazareth, which was cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ified.</hi> Remiſſion of ſinnes, imputation of righteouſnes, validitie of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, inheritance of glorie, they think to receiue from him, which (alas) hath it not for himſelfe. Hath it not, &amp; which is more, hath leſſe meanes to haue it then any, as being moſt contrarie to Chriſt of all. Chriſt hath an high title, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 19.21</note> Reu. 19.21. yet an humble carriage.<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8</note> 
               <hi>He tooke on
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25090:31"/>him the form of a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Phi. 2.8. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the pope hath an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble title, <hi>Seruus ſeruorum Dei,</hi> the ſeruant of the ſeruants of God; but a moſt pompous and pontificall cariage, far exceeding the mightieſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs. Chriſt refuſed ſoueraigntie three times: contrarie, the Pope takes 3. ſoueraignties at once. The ſcriptures ſay of Chriſt, that he is, <hi>&amp; deus, &amp; homo;</hi> both God &amp; man: the Canoniſts ſay of the Pope, that he is, <hi>nec deus nec homo,</hi> neither god nor man. I know not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what to make of him, but verie Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>To come to our ſelues. Who is it but hath a <hi>Ieſus</hi> by himſelfe? The couetous mans <hi>Ieſus</hi> is his money. Did not the rich man hope for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in his riches, when he ſaid,<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Soule, thou haſt much goods laid vp in ſtore for many years<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eate &amp; drinke, and take thine eaſe?</hi> Luk. 12.19. So, the gluttons God, is his belly. <hi>Paul calls it ſo,</hi> Phil. 3.19.<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe God is their bellie, whoſe glorie is to their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25090:31"/>ſhame, which minde earthly things.</hi> So, the ambitious mans God is honour, the laſciuious mans God is pleaſure; &amp; as the heathen ſaith of a man in loue, if he hath what he loueth,<note n="g" place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
               <hi>id habet pro cibo,</hi> it is meate &amp; drinke to him. So I may ſay of euery mans delight, which his minde and heart is ſet vpon, <hi>id habet pro deo,</hi> it is a <hi>Ieſus</hi> vnto him. For there is no man in the world, but, as by nature he deſires his owne ſafetie, ſo by religion he chuſeth his owne Sauiour: religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with men of the world being nothing elſe,<note n="h" place="margin">Lactant. Inſtit. lib. 2. cap. 7.</note> 
               <hi>quam quod cupiditas humane miratar;</hi> but that which a mans fancie is in loue withall. So true it is, which that graue and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Father Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath obſerued,<note n="i" place="margin">Auguſt de ciuit dei lib. 14. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Beatus vult eſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo etiam non ſic viuendo vt poſſit eſſe.</hi> Man would be bleſſed and happie, though he ſo liues, as he neuer treades the right way too it.</p>
            <p>Amongſt theſe many vaine ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25090:32"/>of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> I may moſt fitly inſert the <hi>ſert of</hi> Ieſuites; who becauſe they would make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeue, that they, &amp; none but they; had found <hi>Ieſus,</hi> they haue taken away his name from al others, and appropriated it to themſelues.<note n="k" place="margin">Verbum cauponan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Ieſum vendentes Ignat. ad Trallian.</note> In the meane time, they play the merchants with the word, and the <hi>Indaffas</hi> with <hi>Ieſus.</hi> And whilſt they thus ſeeme to haue gotten <hi>Ieſus</hi> from all others, it is come to paſſe, that they haue loſt Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Let holy <hi>Ign tius</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, ſpeake againſt their <hi>Ignatius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arola,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ignatibid</note> 
               <hi>Qui inim alio nomine appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> praeter iſlud, hic non eſt dei.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is called by any other <hi>name,</hi> then the name of a Chriſtian, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one of Gods. Some therefore call them, not <hi>Ieſuites</hi> but <hi>Iebuſites:</hi> and I thinke, not without verie good cauſe. For as they of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſet vp a company of blind and lame <hi>Iebuſites</hi> on the walls of their citie, in diſgrace of <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">m 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 156</note> when
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:25090:32"/>he came vnto them,<note n="m" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.6.</note> Sam. 5.6. So, they of <hi>Rome</hi> haue ſet vp theſe <hi>Iebuſites (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lind,</hi> through ignorance of the truth; <hi>lame,</hi> through per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſenes in life) on the walls of the city of God, vp to the height of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in the Church, in diſgrace of Chriſt, and all his annointed Kings. But no doubt, as <hi>Dauid</hi> fetched downe thoſe baſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe his<note n="n" place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſoule hated them.</hi> Chriſt will one day plucke downe this proud Sect, and diſperſe them with the breath of his mouth, and diſpatch them with the ſword of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>But I haſt to the third degree. <hi>Yee ſeeke Ieſus of Nazareth.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth this commend more then the former For thus ſome haue ſought him without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in the Geſpell; thus ſome ſeeke him, all for profit in the world.</p>
            <p>Read how vnprofitably ſome haue thus ſought him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.5.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25090:33"/>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had ſought out the moſt curſed death, and were ſeeking the moſt bleſſed perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for that death; they meeting with him, he dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of them, <hi>Whom ſeeke yee?</hi> They (vailing all their villanie, vnder a ſmooth anſwere) ſaid, <hi>Ieſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth.</hi> And whereas others which had ſought him ſo before, hearing his ſweete words, were ouercome with them in ſoule, &amp; went backe to the Prieſts with this anſwere,<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.46.</note> 
               <hi>Neuer man ſpake as this man.</hi> Ioh. 7.46. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now ſeeking him, and hearing his powerfull words, were ouerthrowne by them in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.6.</note> 
               <hi>They went backeward, and fell to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</hi> Ioh. 18.6. O the power of the Maieſtie of Chriſt hidden in the vaile of our fleſh.<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt in Ioh. Tract.</note> 
               <hi>Quid indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caturas faciet, qui iudica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus hoc fecit?</hi> What thinke you, wil he doe, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he comes to iudge the world, that thus could doe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was to be iudged in the world? What wil he do, raigning as a king,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:25090:33"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thus did doe, dying as a captiue?</p>
            <p>Now to this inquiſition, none in the world (in my iudgement) is ſo like as the inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Spaine.</hi> For ther <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth,</hi> is ſtil ſought to be put to death, and crucified in his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers. They ſeeke not <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum crucifixum,</hi> but <hi>Chriſtianos cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifigendos,</hi> not Chriſt crucified, but to crucifie Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Wherein the now Antichriſtian popes of <hi>Rome</hi> exceed in crucltie the former hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Emperours of <hi>Rome;</hi> for what was <hi>Traianes</hi> counſaile to <hi>Plinie?</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Tertull. apologet. capit.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc genus inquirendos non eſſe, obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos vero puniri oportere.</hi> That this kind of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſhuld not be inquired after, when they were cloſe, out onely, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſhed when they were offered. But this moſt bloodie inquiſition will not tarrie til poore chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be brought but (like a cruell mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter, clad in a <hi>Liſanders</hi> Lion-fox-skinne coare) hunts them out by craft, &amp; rootes them out by crueltie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:25090:34"/>
Againe, thus ſome ſeeke him all for profit in the world; whilſt they ſeeke indeed, <hi>Ieſum Nazarenum,</hi> but not <hi>crucifixum;</hi> that is, as<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ludolo. de vit. Chri. par 2. cap. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ex Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt.</note> one interprets it, <hi>Ieſum floridum, but not Ieſum flagellatum:</hi> a <hi>Ieſus</hi> crowned with flowers, but not crowned with thornes. That can take the ſweet bread in the paſſeouer, but not the ſower hearbes. That with <hi>Peter</hi> hold it good bein gwith him in mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> where he was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, but denie him and forſake him, in mount <hi>Caluerie,</hi> where he was transfigured. That will be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſo long as they may gaine either reputation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aduantage in the world thereby: but bid religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and God farewell, when profit and commoditie is not annexed thereto. Such ambodexters there be now adaies,<note n="t" place="margin">Bern: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cant. Serm. 16.</note> 
               <hi>qui veterem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non exuerunt, ſed nouo palliant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> which haue not put off the old man with his Iuſtes, but couered him with the new man, as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25090:34"/>with a cloake. God commanded his people that they ſhould not plow with an oxe and an aſſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor weare a garment of linſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wolſie; but I thinke linſiwolſie was neuer more worne then in this age, it being growne from a qualitie, to a habite. For who is it, but in ſeruing God, ſeekes eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſerue himſelfe? For gaine and outward reſpects, may men preach, and more practiſe religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>viderit vtilitas.</hi> is now the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moderatour of our ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying; and men grow rich in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, ſo farre forth as they grow rich by deuotion.</p>
            <p>To come therefore to the fourth degree; <hi>Yee ſeeke Ieſus of Nazareth which was crucified.</hi> Onely this is abſolutely good, and the reſt no further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they tend to this. This onely purchaſeth matter of true ſecuritie, and herein alone, is iuſt cauſe of reioycing. Herein alone, becauſe,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>God forbid that I ſhould
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25090:35"/>glorie, ſaue in the croſſe of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Matt. hom. 55.</note> 
               <hi>Vellem cum Paulo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dicere,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> I would we could ſay alſo with <hi>Paul, Whereby the world is crucified to me, and I vnto the world,</hi> Gal. 6.16.</p>
            <p>This croſſe of Chriſt, which to the Iewes is a ſcandall, to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles follie, is to the faithfull both of Iewes and Gentiles, <hi>the power of God to ſaluation:</hi> being like <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder, the onely way for vs to climbe vp into heauen,<note n="y" place="margin">Tertul. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ucrſ. Iudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os.</note> 
               <hi>Vt quod perierat olim per lignum in Adam, id reſtitueretur per lignu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti,</hi> That we which periſhed by that which the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> plucked from the tree, might againe be reſtored by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who was faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the tree.<note n="z" place="margin">Bern: in die S. An. dreae. Ser. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt ſilueſtris arbor,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi> It is no barren tree, this ſame tree of the croſſe, but a tree that bare ſuch fruit, as whoſoeuer taſtes of it, ſhall be ſure to liue for euer. Though it were<note n="a" place="margin">Anguſt. de tem p. ſerm. 138.</note> 
               <hi>mortifera Chriſto,</hi> yet it was <hi>Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifera, Chriſtiona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt.</hi> a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25090:35"/>tree to Chriſt, yet the tree of life to a Chriſtian. Hence ſprang the great reioycing and glorying of the fathers in the croſſe.<note n="b" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Matt. hom. 55.</note> 
               <hi>Gloria noſtra, caput &amp; origo beatitudinis, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertas &amp; corona crux eſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> The croſſe, it is our glorie, the head and fountaine of our happineſſe, our libertie from death, and crowne in life. And this, ſaith he, let vs cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out at all times, but then moſt, when the heathens are by vs. Hence came that aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ceremonie, <hi>of ſigning with the croſſe,</hi> ſo much diſtaſted by ſome of our brethren. For when as the Gentiles accounted it fooliſhnes, the Chriſtians to make them aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, purpoſely gloried in it the more. And indeed, the Church, ſaith <hi>Bern:</hi> thinkes nothing more glorious to her ſelfe, then to carrie the diſgrace of her Lord.<note n="c" place="margin">Nihil ſibi glorioſus purat, quam portare ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominiam domini &amp; Bern. Super Cant. Serm. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Grata ignominia crucis ei, qui crucifixo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratus non eſt;</hi> No doubt, to him wil <hi>ye</hi> ſhame of <hi>ye</hi> croſſe be gratefull, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he which indured the ſhame of the croſſe, is gratious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:25090:36"/>
Not that they gloried in a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> croſſe, as they of <hi>Rome</hi> doe. No, it was the vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of Chriſts death vpon the croſſe, which they ſo much glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in. This, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hoc caput certa bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us proprio filio, non pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cit, vt fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiuo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uos ſanaret. Chryſoſt. in Matth. hom. 51.</note> is the fountaine of all good things, that God ſpared not his onely ſonne, to redeeme his vnworthie ſeruants.<note n="e" place="margin">Idem. in Matt. hom. 55.</note> 
               <hi>Paſſio certe domini noſtrae beatitudinis caput eſt.</hi> It is not the wodden croſſe, no, it is the Lords paſſion, that is the fountaine of our happineſſe. Nor ſecondly, that they imputed any vertue to the tranſient croſſe, when it is made in the aire, as they of <hi>Rome</hi> doe. Nay, when they ſigned the bodie at baptiſme, with the croſſe, they taught,<note n="f" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſimpliciter digito in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, ſed magna profecto fide in mente firmare.</hi> Not ſimplie, ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> to ſigne the bodie with the finger, but to ſtrengthen the heart by faith. Nor thirdly, that they crouched to a piece of wood, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:25090:36"/>
               <hi>Holie Croſſe ſaue vs, as they of</hi> Rome <hi>doe;</hi> But when they came to the Sacrament, &amp; there remember the vertue of Chriſts death on the Croſſe; then ſaith bleſſed <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cypria. de coen. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Cruci haeremus, ſanguinem ſugimus, &amp; intra ipſa Redemptoris vulnera, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus lingua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Then cleaue we to the Croſſe, and faſtening our tongue within the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our <hi>Redeemer:</hi> thence ſucke out the bloud of our redemption. Laſtly, not that they adorned a wodden croſſe with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, blue ſilke, &amp;c. as they of <hi>Rome</hi> do: but they adorned their croſſes, with the ſame ornaments that <hi>Chriſt</hi> adorned his Croſſe with all; they were foure vertues, ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Bern. in die Sant. Paſch. Serm. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Supereminentior charitas, &amp;c. Charity</hi> on the top, <hi>obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> on the right hand, <hi>patience</hi> on the left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; <hi>the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation of all vertues, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,</hi> in the bottome. Theſe were the orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which they adorned the croſſe withall, and which they prectiſed, when they ſuffered their martyrdome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:25090:37"/>
Thus, ô deare <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> with theſe holy fathers, with theſe deuout wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, do thou <hi>ſeeke Chriſt Ieſus, and him crucified.</hi> Let thy deuout ſoule, with the <hi>Spouſe</hi> in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> go vp and downe, and make diligent enquirie for him, whom thy ſoule loueth. Make diligent enquiry for him in the Citie, the Citie of God, the Church: in the field, <hi>ſed in cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po Scripturarum,</hi> in the field of the holie Striptures, in the houſe, the houſe of God; there thou ſhalt find him, like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Marie</hi> in the Temple. Let the three faculties of thy ſoule, Reaſon, will, and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, like theſe three holie women, ſtirre in the morning of thy life, to find him in the bed of his graue.</p>
            <p>O how happie will it be for thy erroneous reaſon, to finde him which is<note n="i" place="margin">Bern. ſuper Cant. Serm. 11.</note> 
               <hi>plenitudo Lucis,</hi> the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Light: for thy captiued will, to find him, which is, <hi>multitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> the multitude of Peace: for thy obliuious memorie, to enioy him <hi>which is continuatio Aeternitatis,</hi> the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25090:37"/>continuation of Eternitie. Let this thy miſerable Triplicie of defects,<note n="k" place="margin">O beate &amp; beatificans Trinitas, ad te mea miſera Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliter ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirat. Bern.</note> ſeek that bleſſed, &amp; bleſſed maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g <hi>Trinity,</hi> of fulnes. He is <hi>Veritie, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, Eternitie:</hi> applie him to thy ſeueral wants, &amp; let him be another ſoule to thy ſoule,<note n="l" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 18.</note> that <hi>GOD</hi> may be all in all. When thou haſt found him, doe like the <hi>Spouſe,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>hold him faſt, &amp; let him not gee:</hi> Cant. 3.4. Nay whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nd him, ſeek him ſtil,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſeek the Lord, &amp; his ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ſeek his face euermore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">o Vt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huic inquiſitioni, qua ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car amor, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem praeſtet inuentio, ſed amore creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente, inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio creſcat inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti. Aug. in Pſ. 104.</note> Pſal. 105.4. That which theſe holy wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did in the morning, do thou all thy life long: that ſo, the taſte of him for a time, may not make an end of <hi>ſeeking:</hi> but the <hi>often taſting of him,</hi> may increaſe thy loue to him, and ſo thou maiſt <hi>ſeeke him for euer.</hi> If thou find him for one vertue, <hi>ſeeke him for another. Bern: hath a chaine of</hi> 7. <hi>links, by which the deuout ſoule,</hi> being trained <hi>to ſeek the eternall word,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 84.7.</note> grows fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, till ſhe <hi>appeares before the Lord in Sion,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Per Cant. Serm. 85.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe ſeeks him, to whom ſhee may conſent to amendment:</hi> from
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25090:38"/>whom ſhee may be inlightened to knowledge; by whom ſhe may be initiated to vertue: throgh whom ſhe may be reformed to wiſdome; like whom ſhe may be conformed to comelineſſe; to whom ſhe may be married to fruitfulneſſe; and whom fully and for euer, ſhee may enioy for delight. Be ſtirring then, and linger no longer. Marke how peremptorily the Prophet ſpeakes to thee. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.12.<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.12.</note> 
               <hi>The morning commeth and alſo the night, if you will ſeeke, ſeeke.</hi> If euer you meane to begin, now it is high time. Seeke him in ſimplicitie of heart:<note n="ſ" place="margin">Non aliud tanquam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud praeter il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Bern. exhor. ad Fratr. Serm. 2.</note> not any thing elſe in ſtead of him, not any thing beſide him, not any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g after him. Do this now in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy life, the night comes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no man can worke. Thus haue we heard the wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by reaſon of which, we haue made en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie of many things. Let vs now come to the third part, Chriſts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: <hi>He is riſen, he is not here;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25090:38"/>Behold the place where they put him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this part, 3. things are very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruable. Firſt, the power of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection: <hi>He is riſeu,</hi> ſaith the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell; he was not ſtolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away by his diſciples, nor raiſed by any other, but <hi>Ipſe reſurrexit,</hi> hee alone raiſed vp himſelfe. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, the ſpeed of his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>He is not here,</hi> ſaith he, although your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and your deuotion earneſt, yet both come ſhort of his <hi>preſencee,</hi> he hath preuented you, <hi>He is not here.</hi> Thirdly, the truth of his Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>Behold the place where they put him,</hi> ſaith he. Peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, you may doubt, whether I ſay true, you may (happilie) thinke hee is ſtill in the graue. Come therefore, and ſee, vſe the benefite of your owne eyes, <hi>Behold the place where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y put him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the firſt point, that is, the <hi>Power</hi> of his Reſurrection, it is well inſinuated by the Angell, when hee ſaith, <hi>He is riſen,</hi> He nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no hand to plucke him vp, as
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25090:39"/>others that roſe before him, and it was impoſſible that any hand ſhuld hold him backe, of all that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. As no man tooke away his life,<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.18.</note> hee had power to lay it downe: ſo no man could keepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his life, hee had power to take it againe.</p>
            <p>We read of ſome men, that while they were aliue, had power to raiſe vp the dead, as<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.41.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> raiſed <hi>Tabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> Act. 9. 41. Yea which is more, of ſome, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were dead, had yet a power to raiſe vp other dead, x as <hi>Elizeus,</hi> who but tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the dead Souldiour with his bones, reuiued him, and ſet him on his feete againe.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 13.21</note> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 13 21. But we neuer read of anie man, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, was able to raiſe vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but onely <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth,</hi> which was crucified. And he could do both this &amp; the former. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was liuing, he raiſed vp the dead,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.41.</note> as <hi>Lazarus,</hi> &amp; others, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.41. &amp; which is more, beeing dead, could
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:25090:39"/>raiſe vp other dead; for at his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.52.</note> 
               <hi>the graues opened, &amp; many dead bodies of the Saints aroſe.</hi> Mat. 27.52. And which is moſt of all, himſelfe bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dead, yet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was able to raiſe vp himſelfe, which no man in the world euer did, &amp; which all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world could neuer do. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as he was declared truely to be the <hi>Sonne of man,</hi> by yeelding vnto death; ſo,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4.</note> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> he was decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mightily to be <hi>the Sonne of God,</hi> by <hi>the Reſurrection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead.</hi> Ro. 1.4.<note n="b" place="margin">Bern. paru. Serm. 14.</note> 
               <hi>qui Agnus extitteraet in paſſione, factus eſt Leo in Reſurrectione.</hi> Hee, ſaith <hi>Bern:</hi> that was a Lambe in his Paſſion, became a Lyon in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. When hee was to be crucified,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.7.</note> he was led, ſaith <hi>Iſay,</hi> as a <hi>ſheepe</hi> to the ſlaughter, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.7. But when hee aroſe againe, (it was <hi>Iacobs</hi> Prophecie) that<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.9.</note> 
               <hi>As a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whelpe, hee ſhould come vp from the ſpoyle.</hi> Geneſ. 49 9. From the ſpoyle indeed, that is, from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpoyled, (as a moſt victorious
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25090:40"/>and conquering champion) death, and hell, ſinne and Sathan, with the whole rabble of the infernall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, from all ſuch force, as they had gotten againſt him, and all his members.</p>
            <p>Hence it is well obſerued, that Chriſts reſurrection hath a double <hi>priuiledge</hi> aboue the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or rather, reſuſcitation of all others. For though others roſe from the dead as well as Chriſt, yea, and in time, before him: yet, ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Bern. in die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Paſch. Serm. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Reſurrexerant mortui, iterum morit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri.</hi> They roſe indeed, when they were dead, but yet, to die a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine when they were raiſed.</p>
            <p>But<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rem.</hi> 6.9</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt riſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, dieth no more, death hath no more power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him.</hi> Ro. 6 9. And therfore, iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is hee called<note n="g" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Primitiae dormien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> the firſt fruites of them that deepe, which only roſe to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alitie,<note n="h" place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Et fic reſurrexit vt cadere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on adijciat,</hi> roſe in ſuch manner at once, as he was to fall againe neuer after.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:25090:40"/>
Againe, all thoſe which had power giuen them to raiſe others, yet had no power to raiſe themſelues. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeus</hi> that raiſed vp another man dead, yet hath no power to raiſe vp himſelfe.<note n="i" place="margin">Bern: ibi ſupra.</note> Loe how many yeares hath he liue in the graue, expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ioyfull reſurrection at his hand, which hath triumphed ouer the graue; by which it appeares, that all ſuch as raiſed others, did it, <hi>poteſtate precariâ, non propriâ,</hi> by a power, not reſiant in themſelues, but receiued from God.</p>
            <p>But Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Bern: in die Sanct. Paſ. Ser. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute propria victor prodijt de Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chro;</hi> by his owne power raiſed vp himſelfe, and by the ſtrength of his owne arme, made all things giue way vnto him.<note n="l" place="margin">Amb. de virg. lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Erras mulier</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe, quae putas de monumento Chriſtum eſſe ſublatum.</hi> O woman, that thinkeſt ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath taken away thy Lord, and laid him thou knoweſt not where, thou erreſt groſely. This victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:25090:41"/>
               <hi>Sampso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſtoutly caried away the gates of<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>Azzah,</hi> burſt ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> dore of his Tombe, where the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Iewes had ſhut him; &amp; in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when they ſought him, was riſen, was not there.</p>
            <p>But the womans errour Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſalueth,<note n="n" place="margin">Hieron. ad Hedibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quaeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Error mulieris cum pietate ſocietus eſt;</hi> An errour of infirmitie, ioyned with deuotion. But the Iewes, who can excuſe? O fooliſh Iewes, tell vs, why did you ſeale and locke downe the ſtone ſo faſt? Becauſe (ſaid ſome of your rulers)<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.63.</note> 
               <hi>We remember that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer ſaid, within three daies I will riſe vp again.</hi> Ma. 27.63.<note n="p" place="margin">Bern:in die. Sanct. Paſ. Ser. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vere ſeduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern: Sed pius, non malitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> A deceiuer he is indeed, but an <hi>holy,</hi> not a malicious deceiuer: and you may well ſay with <hi>Ieremiah</hi> your Prophet,<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord thou haſt deceiued me, and I am deceiued, thou art ſtronger then I, and haſt preuailed. Ierem.</hi> 20.7. What thinke you of him now? Is he ſtill but the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:25090:41"/>ſonne? A Carpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters ſonne he is we grant, <hi>Sed</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Bern:</note> 
               <hi>hominis fabri filius, fabricator hominis,</hi> the ſonne of man, and ſuch a Carpenter, as made man, and all the world. Will you ſtill be obſtinate? Will you not yet beleeue? You will ſay, <hi>If he had come downe from the croſſe, we would haue beleeued in him.</hi> Indeed ſo ſaid ſome of your rulers,<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.42.</note> 
               <hi>Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendet de cruce, &amp;c.</hi> Matt. 27.42. But ô how like their father the diuell, ſpeake theſe wicked children, ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Serm. de pasſione.</note> The diuell ſaid, Caſt thy ſelfe downeward from the <hi>Temple;</hi> and theſe men ſay, <hi>Let him come downe from the croſſe.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Fraudu. lenta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misſio. Hie. rom.</note> But all this is but diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling. For,<note n="x" place="margin">Bern: in die Sa Paſ. Serm. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Si non creditis reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti, nec credidiſſetis deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aenti.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if you beleeue him not riſing out of the graue, neither would you haue beleeued in him, if he had come downe from the croſſe. Leauing then theſe obſtinate
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25090:42"/>Iewes in the depth of their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, till the time of refreſhing comes; Let vs proceed to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point, the ſpeed of his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in theſe words, <hi>he is not here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Angell declares, that though theſe women were earely comming to him, yet Chriſt was riſen and gone before their comming at him. I may iuſtly therfore apply this ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpeech, to the ſpeed of his reſurrection. Who though he were to anſwere the figure, which himſelf ſpake of, Mat. 12.40. <hi>As</hi> Ionas <hi>was three daies and three nights in the whales bellie, ſo muſt the ſonne of man be three daies and three nights in the heart of the earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">y <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.40.</note> yet in verie truth, he was not ſo long time in the bowels of the earth, as <hi>Ionas</hi> was in the bellie of the fiſh. For about the ninth houre, he died on the croſſe: and about three houres after that, was he laid into his graue. Now this, in our account, was about three of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:25090:42"/>the clocke in the afternoone. This is but a ſmall part of a day, yet this is reckoned for the firſt day. The ſecond day, being the day of reſt to the Iewes, he himſelf alſo reſted in his graue. The third day, being the firſt day of the weeke, ſo ſoone as the ſunne of the firmament roſe to cheare the eies of the world, this glorious Sonne of righteouſnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe alſo, to cheare the harts of the elect. Here you ſee is but one whole day, with the end of that which went before it, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that which followed after it: and yet it is reckoned for three daies, and that iuſtly; for the firſt day, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> is taken,<note n="z" place="margin">Auguſt lib. de Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Secundum partem ſui poſteriorem,</hi> according to the latter part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d day, <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe totam &amp; integram,</hi> according to it ſelfe, whole &amp; intire: the third, <hi>Secu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum partem ſui prima,</hi> onely according to the former part thereof.</p>
            <p>And what may be the reaſon of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25090:43"/>this haſt, may you ſay. If any think he thus haſted away, leaſt his bodie ſhould putrifie, he thinkes amiſſe. For ſeeing putrifaction is a puniſhment of ſinne, then ſurely there was no reaſon that Chriſt ſhould feare corruption; For (as <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in another caſe ſaith)<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. de ciuit. dei lib. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Cur eſſet vllo paena, vbi non erant vlla punienda?</hi> Why ſhould there be any feare of puniſhment, where nothing was found due to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? In verie deed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cauſes were theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Vt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta fidelis inueniatur. Bern: in die Sanct. Paſ. Ser. 1.</note> that the prophet might be found faithfull, who ſaith, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2.</note> He (that is) <hi>the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>ſhall quicken vs after two daies, and the third day, he ſhall raiſe vs vp, and we ſhall come into his preſence.</hi> Wherein he ſignifieth the ſmall time that Chriſt was to remaine in his graue.</p>
            <p>No doubt but death, as he was very greedie to deuour Chriſt, ſo he was verie deſirous to retaine him. But <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>It was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:25090:43"/>that he ſhould be held of the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of death.</hi> Act. 2.24. That which death did, and doth, to all other men, ſwallow and deuour; he was not able to do to the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſus; but<note n="e" place="margin">O mors ero mors tua ero morſus tuus inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Hoſ. 13.14.</note> was ſwallowed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured himſelfe. And looke as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> ſtomacke could brooke all the allowed fruits: but when he came to the tree in the midſt of the garden, and taſted of it, he ſet his teeth on edge and ſurfeited: euen ſo death, that feedes vpon all other fleſh, and can brooke it well enough, when he would needs be feeding on this mediator of God &amp; man, ſurcharged his ſtomacke, ſurfeited of ſweet meate, &amp; within three daies vomitted him vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, out of his bowells.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he aroſe within three daies, that there might be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine reſemblance, and analogie, betweene the two great workes of the creation of the world, and the redemption of the world.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25090:44"/>At the beginning in the ſixt day of the weeke, God created man. The next day God reſted from all his workes. <hi>The third day he ceaſed from his reſt.</hi> Euen ſo, Chriſt Ieſus, the ſixt day of the weeke, redeemed man on the croſſe, being the verie day wherein he made him at the firſt. The day following,<note n="f" place="margin">Bern: in die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anct. Paul. Serm. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſabbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zauit in monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> he kept ſabboth in the graue. And the third day, as the firſt fruits of the dead, he appeared a new man in the face of the earth. Yea, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly himſelfe, was then become new, but euen all the creatures became new againe with him, and the whole world ſeemed to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, for ioy of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>And, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſaith, the budding of plants, bloſſoming of trees, an ſpringing of flowers, ſufficiently witneſſed,<note n="g" place="margin">Lactan. in carminibus.</note> 
               <hi>Omnia cum domino dona rediſſe ſuo,</hi> that all the creatures were returned from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25090:44"/>death with their Lord: and wee may now fitlie with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iſay,</hi> ſing,<note n="h" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17 <hi>Iſ.</hi> 43.19.</note> 
               <hi>Olde things are done away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, all things are now become new.</hi> 2. Cor. 5.17.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee aroſe within three dayes, to be a type vnto vs of our condition after him. There is not one of vs, but hath, and ſhall haue (as Chriſt) our three dayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a day of ſuffering in this life. Secondly, a day of reſt in the graue. Thirdly, a day of reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vp againe.</p>
            <p>Now he hath inſtructed vs, what wee muſt doe in thoſe dayes, and what thoſe dayes ſhall be vnto vs.</p>
            <p>In this firſt day of ours wherein we liue,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16 24.</note> we muſt <hi>take vp our Croſſe and follow him.</hi> Matth. 16.24.<note n="k" place="margin">Bern. in die ſanct. Paſch. Serm. I.</note> 
               <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem audiamus fratres,</hi> ſaith Saint Bernard, <hi>non carnem &amp; ſanguinem, non ſpiritum quemlibet deſcenſum a Cruce ſuadentem.</hi> Brethren, if anie man in the world, if our owne fleſh and bloud, if anie manner of ſpirit
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:25090:45"/>counſell vs to come downe from the croſſe, let vs heare none of them all.</p>
            <p>Yea, if our deereſt friendes bid vs fauour our ſelues, as <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let vs replie to euery one, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.23.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee behino me Sathan, thou art an offence vnto me.</hi> Mat. 16.23.</p>
            <p>Thus if we ſpend the firſt day, at the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d day, the day of our death, we ſhall reſt with Chriſt ſweetly, we ſhall ſleepe quietlie in the graue. For Chriſt hath gone to bed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before vs, as it were, to warme it againſt our comming.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note n="m" place="margin">In Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</note> 
               <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pultura Christi, quies Chriſtiani:</hi> The buriall of Chriſt, is the reſt of a Chriſtian. By it, Chriſt hath both abated the ſting of the paine, and alſo increaſed the ſtrength of the patient. For looke as the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was content to be caſt into a ſleepe, and to haue a ribbe or bone took from him, to make a wife, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25090:45"/>to haue the place filled vp with ſoft fleſh againe: Euen ſo, the ſecond <hi>Adam, CHRISTIESVS,</hi> was content to be caſt into the ſleep of death, to giue <hi>a bone,</hi> that is, <hi>ſtrength and Fortitude,</hi> vnto his Spouſe the Church, &amp; haue receiued nothing from her for it, but onely the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and weakneſſe of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Now if we be crucified with him the firſt day, &amp; reſt with him the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day, the third day<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2:</note> 
               <hi>he wil raiſe vs vp, &amp; we ſhall com into his preſence. Hoſ.</hi> 6.2. For ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rmo.</hi> 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>If we ſuffer together with him, we ſhall raigne with him in glorie. Rom.</hi> 8.17. Indeed we alſo graunt, the wicked ſhall riſe: but not by vertue of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, but by the power of the iuſt iudgement of God. They ſhall riſe I ſay, but not to life:<note n="p" place="margin">Bern. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Cent. Serm. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Imo ad vitam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern. vt vim in morte, infoelicius moriantur:</hi> yea, to life too, in ſome ſort; that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a dying life, and dying a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing death, they may euer liue in moſt direful &amp; deadly damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:25090:46"/>
But the righteous ſhalbe ſure, as they liued to Chriſt in this world, ſo to liue with him in the world to come; For <hi>Pauls</hi> rule is certaine.<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>If the ſpirit of him that raiſed vp Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus dwell in you, hee that raiſed</hi> Chriſt <hi>from the dead, ſhall alſo quicken your mortall bodies, by his ſpirit that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he aroſe within three dayes, that he might not any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger perplex the hearts of his diſciples. When he died, one ſold him, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foreſwore him; &amp; all forſooke him. When he was dead, and riſen againe, ſome belieued, ſome doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſome were reſolute in vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</p>
            <p>If they were thus perplexed, when hee tarryed from them but three dayes, what would they haue bene, if he had abſented himſelfe three weekes? Therefore, ſaith <hi>Leo: Ne</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam tridui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am tam mira celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate breuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, vt dum ad integ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundum diem pars primi nouiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima, &amp; pars certij prima concurrit, &amp; aliquantulu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſpacio te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, poris deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret, &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil de dieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> numero de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periret. Leo de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurr. Dom. Serm. 1.</note> 
               <hi>turbatos Diſcipulorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimos long a moeſtitudo cruciaret, &amp;c.</hi> That continuall ſadneſſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:25090:46"/>ſhould not perpetuallie vexe the diſciples hearts, the Lord abbreui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the appointed time of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the graue: that whileſt the latter part of the firſt day, and the firſt part of the latter day, be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as dayes, no part of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber doth periſh, for falſifying the Scriptures, and yet a great part of their le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth is cut off, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his diſciples. And whereas he was abſent from them in the graue, for the ſpace of fortie houres; he afterwards came, and remained with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, for the ſpace of fortie dayes.</p>
            <p>And mark (with me) further, from hence a worthie point. So earlie in the morning was <hi>Chriſt</hi> riſen from the dead, that thogh theſe women, which came with oyntments and odors to embalme him, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming (as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith)<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>while it was yet darke, Ioh.</hi> 20.1. Yet ſuch was the ſpeedy vpriſing of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> that he was gone ere they came.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:25090:47"/>
Shall wee thinke Chriſt ſcorned their good deuotion, now hee was riſen, which hee accepted kindely, ere hee was crucified? Some of them had annoynted him liuing, and he tooke it gratiouſly: his feet with teares, his head and feet both, with ſpikenard.</p>
            <p>Shall wee thinke hee now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, what before he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? No, ſaith <hi>Bern:</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Bern. ſuper Cant. Serm. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Renuit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, ſed parcens, non ſpernens:</hi> hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed indeed to be annoynted, but ſparing the annointed, not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpriſing the annointers.</p>
            <p>Shall we thinke then that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to delude and beguile theſe ſimple women? Not ſo neither, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Mulierum deuotioni, non cluſit, ſed inſtruxit.</hi> This deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theirs, he intended not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, but laboured to inſtruct.</p>
            <p>What may it be then? Take it in a word. When they came with ſpices and oyntments to perſume his dead bodie, he refuſed it: tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25090:47"/>them euer after, how their deuotion ſhould be pleaſing vnto him: that is to ſay, not to ſpend anie thing vpon his dead bodie in the graue; but to beſtow all vpon his liuing bodie the Church.<note n="x" place="margin">Bern. vt ſup.</note> 
               <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam vngi, ipſam foueri deſiderat:</hi> The church, the church I ſay, his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Spouſe, that is it which Chriſt deſires ſhould be annointed.</p>
            <p>The miniſters, her mouth and teeth, which breake the bread of eternall life, together with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her feeble members, would Chriſt haue to be ſweetened with the perfumes of your moſt holie deuotions, that ſo your liberalitie to the church, may prooue like the <hi>Philippians</hi> benificence to <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.18.</note> an odour that ſmelleth ſweete, a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice pleaſing, and acceptable to God. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p>Heerein, beſides the precept of Chriſt, to informe and commaund vs, haue wee alſo the practiſe of good Chriſtians, to reforme and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:25090:48"/>
And, that I may not goe any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then where we are, the former benefactors to this preſent place, call for after benefites of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding age, plentifullie to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed to the good of the Church.</p>
            <p>That worthie Ladie <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Shrewsburie,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great ſumme of money into the hands of that Reuerend father, <hi>Iohn Ailmer,</hi> ſometime Biſhop of this Sea, for the better promiſion of thoſe Preachers, which are ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this place.</p>
            <p>O how right this fittes with my former aſſertion, that women by grace, equall men in vertue, as by nature they come not behind them in wit. Whoſe example ſo moued the Reuerend father, that hee gaue out of his owne reuenues, three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, &amp; made of one hundred pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, foure, for the ſame end and purpoſe. There in he proued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a <hi>Iohn,</hi> in that, though he did not at firſt goe out with her, yet
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:25090:48"/>afterwards, hee did out goe her. For who ſhould outſtrip all men in good example, if not Biſhops? and who ſhould ſhine forth to others, but ſuch as be the Lights of the world.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, one <hi>Thomas Ruſſell,</hi> a good Citizen, added a yearely penſion of ten pounds, to the end aboueſaid, to teach you Citizens, that as you haue euer bene recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the forwardeſt in good works, ſo you ſhould be moued by his example, both to reteine, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to increaſe that good reputation that hath bin had of you: that ſo, neither the way-faring Prophet (who formerly with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> hath bin forced to lodge among ſcorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) may from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth want, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a chamber, or a bed, or a table, and candleſtick: nor the Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger accuſe our religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes, ſaying we preach Faith, but ouerthrow <hi>all good works:</hi> &amp; that our religion is like the fig-tree, hauing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:25090:49"/>manie faire leaues of doctrine, but little or no fruit of good life. And thus much touching the ſecond point.</p>
            <p>The third part followes, and that is the trueth of his Reſurrection: <hi>Behold the place where they put him.</hi> A if he had ſaid, <hi>Si non creditis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculo, credite oculo.</hi> If you cannot for ioy, conceiue the meaning of my wordes, or for ſorrow belieue the truth of my words, looke into the graue, ſee the place emptie, and him gone: <hi>Behold the place where they put him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this point (I truſt) I may be briefe. Certainly, I ſhould doe you iniurie to vrge it much, ſeeing you are all (as I truſt) good Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; belieue it to be moſt true. And my much labour in prouing the truth thereof, might inſinuat a ſuſpition of your want of faith therin,<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſanct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch Serm. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Qui nouit defendere fidem,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, titubartius eſt neceſſarius, non credentibus:</hi> He that knowes how
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:25090:49"/>to defend the ſaith, is more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for him that doubteth, then profitable for him that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth.</p>
            <p>But put caſe there were ſome <hi>Iewe</hi> here, or <hi>Pagan;</hi> Is it poſſible that he ſhuld not belieue the truth of Chriſts Reſurrection? Let him with theſe women, vſe the hene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his eyes. Let him looke to the manifold Prophecies and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures concurrences, that happened together with it: and the often and vndoubted Apparitions that came to paſſe after it.</p>
            <p>At the beginning, euen <hi>GOD</hi> himſelfe declared it by Prophecie,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 15. <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head. Dauid</hi> afterward is bold and ſaith:<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not leaue my ſoule in hell, nor ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thine Holie one to ſee corruption.</hi> Pſalm. 16.10. And what meant<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>Adams</hi> ſleepe till <hi>Euah</hi> was taken out of his ſide, and his waking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:25090:50"/>to liue with her as a louing huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, but that Chriſt alſo ſhould ſleepe in the graue, that out of his pierced ſide, the Spouſe might be purchaſed, to whom hee ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after wake, as a moſt vigilant and carefull defender?</p>
            <p>What was ſignified by<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.11.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaack,</hi> laid as a Sacrifice on the Altar, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be offred, but preſently lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and vnbound againe; but that <hi>CHRIST IESVS,</hi> the true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the ſinnes of the whole world, ſhould be offred to death on the Altar of the Croſſe, and the ſorrows of death, immediately lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againe, whereof it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that hee ſhould be holden?</p>
            <p>This glorious Reſurrection of the <hi>SONNE OF GOD,</hi> was further ſignified by <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.14.</note> who a few dayes was impriſoned in the dungeen, &amp; afterwards, aduanced to the regiment of a Kingdome.</p>
            <p>By<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15 14.</note> 
               <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who while he ſlept was bound with ropes, but when
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:25090:50"/>he awaked againe, ſnapped them in ſunder as threeds.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ionas,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ion.</hi> 2.10</note> who was ſwallowed of a fiſh, but after three dayes caſt vpon drie land againe.</p>
            <p>Looke further, on the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences happening together with it, as the great Earth-quake<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.2.</note> which then was. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.2.</p>
            <p>Sure, ſaith <hi>Hilarie,</hi> it was the vertue of his Reſurrection, and ſignified, that<note n="f" place="margin">Aquin. in Cate, ſuper Mat. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Reſurgente virtutum coeleſtium domino, inferorum trepida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mouetur.</hi> The Lord of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly powers ariſing, the weaknes of the infernall powers ſhould be troubled.</p>
            <p>Conſider the huge ſtone rolled &amp; turned away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the graue, with the handſome folding of the cloathes and napkins left behin de him, and weigh ſeriouſlie that ſame tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Lie of the keepers; how euen then they proue <hi>Christs reſurection to be true:</hi> when they went about to make the world belieue it was falſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:25090:51"/>They being therevnto hyred with money, gaue out, that <hi>His diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples came by night,</hi>
               <note place="margin">g <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.13.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtole him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, whilſt they were ſleeping.</hi> Matth. 28.13.</p>
            <p>But ô Children of the diuell, how abſurdlie doe you ſpeake? For if you ſlept, how can you tell hee was ſtollen away? and if you were awake, why doe you ſay you ſlept?</p>
            <p>Againe, recount the manie Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions that he made after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. If I be not deceiued, <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; the Euangeliſts reckon ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſeuerall Apparitions of Chriſt after his Reſurrection: for more confirmation of the truth thereof, Sometime he appeared to comfort the ſorrowfull hearts of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: ſometime to conuince the obſtinate hearts of his enemies. Sometime hee eate meate with them, &amp; ſhewed them his wounds, which hee kept, ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Auguſt, in die Sanct. Paſch. Serm. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Non ageſtate, ſed poteſtate,</hi> not for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:25090:51"/>any weakneſſe in himſelfe, but for the ſtrengthening of others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, <hi>vt ſanaret vulnus incredulita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis:</hi> That the apparant woundes of his crucified bodie, might heale the hidden ſores of their vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoules.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>Hee was ſeene of more then fiue hundreth bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theren at once: and laſtly of mee, as of one borne out of due time.</hi> 1. Corinth. 15.6.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus cleare, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture now you will wonder, why the <hi>Iewes</hi> belieue not <hi>Chriſts reſurrection to be true?</hi> Surely, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon can be yeelded of it, but this, that partly obſtinacie is come vpon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> till the fulneſſe of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> be come in. And <hi>certes,</hi> euen wee which belieue the trueth thereof, are not beholding to our ſelues for it. It may be ſaide to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie faithfull ſoule among vs, as Chriſt ſaide to <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>Fleſh and blood hath not reuealed this vnto thee:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:25090:52"/>but my Father which is in heauen.</hi> Matth. 16.17. For though <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>Why ſhould it be thought a thing incredible vnto you, that God ſhould raiſe againe the dead?</hi> Act. 26.8. And indeed, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note n="m" place="margin">Concide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra autorem &amp; tolle du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitationem. Auguſt in die San. Paſ. Ser. 4.</note> There is no cauſe of doubting, if we conſider the authour: yet ſuch is our obſtinate blindneſſe by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the moſt eaſie, plaine &amp; true things, are hard, harſh, and falſe in our iudgement, till,<note n="n" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>We haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſpirit of God, that we may knowe the things which be of God.</hi> 1. Cor. 2.12. In this regard, the faith of Chriſt generally embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the world, is numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the moſt famous myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our religion.<note n="o" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, great is the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of godlines, God is manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, preached vnto the Gentiles,</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEEVED ON IN THE WORLD, <hi>and receiued vp into glorie.</hi> 1. Tim. 3.16. Hereupon <hi>Bern:</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:25090:52"/>hath this obſeruation,<note n="p" place="margin">Bern: in vigili. Nat. dom. Ser. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tria opera, tres mixturas, &amp;c.</hi> That omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maieſtie in the aſſumption of our fleſh, did three workes, made three mixtures, ſo ſingularly maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and ſo maruellouſly ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that as he neuer did them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo he was to doe them neuer after, <hi>Coniuncta ſunt quippe ad in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, deus &amp; homo, mater &amp; virgo, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; cor humanum.</hi> For there were ioyned together, God and man, a mother and a Virgin, faith &amp; mans ſoule. The like alſo hath <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerued.<note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt de ciuit. de. lib. 22. cap. 5.</note> There are three incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible things, ſaith he, and yet haue they bin done. It is incredible that Chriſt ſhould ariſe in our fleſh, and that he ſhould aſcend vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our fleſh: and thirdly, <hi>incredible eſt, mundum, remtam incredibilem credidiſſe,</hi> it is alſo incredible, that the world ſhould giue credit, to ſo incredible a matter.</p>
            <p>To conclude then. As faith bids vs beleeue the truth hereof, ſo,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:25090:53"/>
               <note n="r" place="margin">I am quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe illum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit fidei, ſed adhue eum quaerit ſpes. Aug. in Pſal. 104.</note> hope requires vs to expect the power hereof: that is, that Chriſt our head, which once aroſe in his owne perſon, ſhall in due time alſo quicken vs his members, in our perſons: that ſo the head and the bodie, being coupled together, God may be all in all.</p>
            <p>And let this hope be vnto vs an author, in all the ſtormes of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, to ſaue our ſoules from ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke. What ſaith <hi>Paul;</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall condemne? It is Chriſt which is dead.</hi> Yea, ſo the Iewes and Pagans be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> therefore <hi>Paul</hi> addes, yea, or rather <hi>which is riſen againe.</hi> This none beleeues but a Chriſtian. And in a ſound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing hereof, conſiſteth the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſaluation of our ſoules.<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 10.9.</note> 
               <hi>For if thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and beleeue in thine heart that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi> Rom. 10.9. Thus <hi>Iob</hi> comforted himſelfe,<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25.</note> 
               <hi>I know that my redeemer liueth, and that he
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:25090:53"/>ſhall ſtand the laſt on the earth.</hi> Iob. 19.25. It is our duetie then, with patience to expect that in our ſelues, which through power we beleeue God effected in him, and when death ſhall approach vs, as it were wholly to deuour vs; then, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort our ſelues, with the thought of this, that,<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.16.</note> 
               <hi>Though after our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, wormes deſtroy this bodie, yet in the appointed time, we ſhall ſee God in our fleſh.</hi> Iob. 19.16. which God, the Father, with his deare Sonne our Sauiour, and the holy Ghoſt our comforter, three perſons, and one euerlaſting God, be all honour and glorie, Maieſtie and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, aſcribed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
